So the first thing I want to talk about is
a very simple, what the textbook calls value
function based methods right, what the textbook
calls value function based methods these are
approaches where I do not know the q star
right but I am going to try and form a estimate
of the q star. So how can I do that so what
is q star the expected payoff right.
So I play each action, I choose each action
say 10 times I can take the average of that
gives me an estimate for q star right. So
we will denote the estimates by Qt. So whenever
we attach a estimate to an action we will
be using the notation Q this is just, so that
you know so we use Q here, and whenever we
will attach a estimate of the payoffs to a
state we will denote it by V, V stands for
value function okay that is easy to remember
do not ask me what Q stands for.
So one of the problems with RL is that because
there are so many different influences that
came in right. So you have at least three
different sets of notations that people use
in the literature okay. So you would have
to swap back and forth if you are reading
papers in reinforcement learning right, so
somebody will say that the value function
is denoted by J right and Q denotes the cost
function right.
So if they had used disjoint set of symbols
at least is easy for us right, but they will
use the same symbol that one body of literature
will call the value function another body
will call that the payoff function right which
essentially corresponds to the reward that
you are getting at every time right. So that
will be denoted by Q, so then all kinds of
confusions are there. So this is one set of
notation that I am choosing essentially because
it is the one that is adopted in the Sutton
and Barto book.
In fact people who are reading edition one
right there has been a overhaul of notation
in edition 2 right. So to the extent possible
I will try to follow the edition 2 notation,
but edition 1 is ingrained in me right, so
I mean, I have been using edition 1 notation
for god knows, 15 years or something right.
So suddenly they decided to change the notation
in edition 2, so by force of habit I might
slip into edition 1 notation occasionally
so it is in your well-being to read ahead
so that you can correct me whenever I do that
right. So do not wait for me to teach and
then go and or well do not wait for the quizzes
and then read the book right.
But read ahead and come to class okay. This
will certainly help you significantly in following
the material better right. So I am deliberately
going slow today warming you up okay. But
then there is lot lot of material that we
cover in fact usually I cover the material
in the book in about one and a half months
right and the rest of the time I will be doing
material outside the book right one and a
half months, two months okay.
And the book is big right so at some point
I will switch modes and start going fast.
So reading ahead helps okay, so we are going
to have Qt so essentially what you can do
is you can just take whenever
I took action a right the reward I got at
that time and I can just keep adding those
up and divide by the number of times I took
action a that will give me my Qt right.
So how will we write this, let us look at
introduce some notation so that is a notation
that I will use whenever I want an indicator
function right. So normally what is the notation
that people use for indicator functions I
or delta right, so people typically use delta
or I so I will use 1 because we use I and
delta for other things later on okay.
So this essentially means that it is 1 whenever
at is a otherwise it is 0 times Rt right,
so what should I divide this by Okay, so this
gives me the average right great. So once
I have this now I have made an estimate for
my q stars right. Once I have an estimate
for my q stars so how will I select an action
apologies okay. So I use t on the left hand
side so I cannot use t as the running variable
as well okay. So now I have come to time t,
I have this estimates for my q stars.
So how can I use that for selecting actions
select the maximum right. So I could be what
we call greedy right, so greedy would be I
am going to select, right. So I will take
that action that gives me the max, alright.
So argmax is the action that gives me the
max right, so I will take that action that
gives me the max and use that as the action
to perform at that time right.
Is that a good choice or alternatively what
does this choice correspond to exploitation
this choice corresponds to exploitation, but
I cannot just exploit right I have to explore
as well, I cannot come up with an algorithm
that only exploits right. So what do you think
will happen let us say that I pulled an arm
right the first time well I select an action
and then you get a reward of 1 let us say
right.
So what will happen to my Q it will be one,
what about my other Qs, well depends on what
you initialize them with, if you initialize
them with 0 they will stay at zero, right
I could have initialized them with 100 right
or I could have initialized them with -100
I do not know whatever it is I initialize
them with they will stay there, but this one
will become one right.
Now if I am doing greedy what will happen
I will do this again let us assume that I
get a 1 again right, and then I keep getting
one every time I pull this. So what will happen
is I will never ever sample any of the other
arms right. It could very well be that arm
3 has a reward of 50 right, right just because
I happen to pull arm one the first time right,
I will never ever go and pull arm 3 even though
it has a much, much higher reward right.
So we do not want to be exploitative completely
so we need to have some kind of a exploration
policy okay. So the simple exploration policy
okay, so I am going to confuse you a little
bit is called
epsilon greedy nothing to do with this epsilon
okay. So this epsilon is completely different
okay, it talks about a solution concept and
just because I have something epsilon greedy
does not mean I am going to give you some
epsilon pac guarantee okay.
This is a completely different epsilon in
fact it was named epsilon greedy before people
even started thinking about bringing all this
pac optimality equations into RL okay. So
what does epsilon greedy means any guesses
sorry, within epsilon of the greedy choice
okay good choice. But I said this has nothing
to do with this epsilon it has got nothing
to this epsilon, what I do is with probability
1 minus epsilon I will be greedy okay, with
probability epsilon I will just explore okay.
So epsilon greedy means with 1 minus epsilon
I will choose with probability 1 minus epsilon
with probability epsilon I will choose uniformly
from the set of actions A okay. So it is one
thing which you should note here is that if
I choose uniformly from A I still have a probability
of hitting that argmax A right. So in fact
the probability of me taking this action is
1 minus epsilon plus epsilon by n right.
The probability of me exploring is actually
n minus 1 epsilon by n okay, so this is something
which is just a small thing nit picking thing
but just remember that. So the probability
of exploration is not epsilon okay because
I am picking uniformly random you could choose
to say that I pick uniformly from A minus
this argmax action right does not make a difference,
but I am just pointing out that there is a
small difference just remember that okay.
So epsilon greedy by far is one of the most
popular exploration is by far the most popular
exploration strategy that people adopt okay,
by far the most popular exploration strategy.
There is another one which ironically I could
not find in edition 2 of the book which is
also rather popular is called softmax or maybe
I flipped through edition 2 too quickly to
notice it, but so the soft max exploration
policy does something slightly cleverer okay.
So if you think about the epsilon greedy what
is it that you would notice is that I have
the best action, the best according to my
current estimates right. So when I say, whenever
I say greedy or best it is according to my
current estimate it is not q stars okay, it
is according to capital Q whenever I say greedy
is according to capital Q okay.
So the greedy action gets the bulk of the
probability right, and every other action
has a equal probability of being picked in
exploration correct. But then if some actions
are clearly bad right if I figure out some
actions are clearly bad, so I do not want
to be picking them during exploration, because
I know that they are bad I really do not want
to be picking them during exploration or at
least I want to reduce the probability of
picking them during exploration right.
And if two actions look equally likely to
be good right maybe 0.0001 difference right
some small delta difference between the two
actions in epsilon greedy what will happen
the one that is that 0.0001 higher will get
the highest probability okay the other one
will have the same probability as the all
the other arms of being picked right.
But then in reality I just want to be able
to compare these two things more closely and
figure out which one is better right, because
the difference is so small I really want to
compare them and figure out which one is better
right. So what people did was they came up
with this soft max idea right where instead
of giving all the probability to one action
right I make the probability of picking the
actions proportional to the estimate, current
estimate.
So whatever is the current Q I will make the
probability proportional to the Q right. So
ideally it should be something like, so this
should be the probability with which
at the t th step I will pick action a right
that should be the probability right, what
is the problem with that. different orders
yeah, different signs right.
So I mean the things could be also negative
numbers inside you I could even end up with
a negative probability right, if my Qt of
a was minus 1 then I will end up with a minus
something as the probability of picking that
action does not make sense right. So to encompass
all kinds of options what do we do, we exponentiate
right.
So why is this called soft max because it
is not greedy does not return to you the one
that has the highest Q value all the time,
but if there is a big difference it will return
that value to you most often. Lets suppose
there are four actions right and action 1
has a value of say 19, action 2 has a value
of 1.2, action 3 has a value of 0.7, action
4 has a value of minus 0.3 right.
So now this will return to you most often
it will return action 1 to you right, so because
that has a significantly higher value okay
that is why it is called soft max right. Sometimes
what people do is they throw in another parameter
called the temperature parameter sometimes
so beta right. So now think about if beta
is very, very high.
So what will happen to your soft max function
everything will get squished down right, so
beta is very, very high. So essentially you
will be behaving at random, uniformly random
right because all the regardless of what the
Q values are right if the beta is very, very
let us say beta is 1 million right and I say
17 and 1.8 no, no it does not make any difference
right, all of them will look close to 0 right.
So essentially I will be picking all actions
uniformly randomly right, this way it is called
temperature. So if you are very, very hot
right so things will move around at random
right and then people typically cool it down
say they make beta smaller and smaller and
smaller so that from a very high temperature
where you are essentially behaving at random
regardless of what the Q values are as you
keep cooling it down it becomes more and more
peaked.
So if beta becomes closer and closer to 0
what happens it becomes max right as beta
goes to zero this function goes to max so
it become greedy. So it gives an additional
parameter for tuning right if you do not trust
me you can work it out right you guys are
smart enough to work it out. So this gives
you an additional parameter for tuning how
sharp your probability needs to fall right.
So this is called soft max and so if we think
about epsilon greedy then writing it in this
notation. So this will be right, so
probability at equals a star will be 1 minus
epsilon plus epsilon by n where a star is
the greedy action according to the current
estimate right. The probability at is not
equal to a star or probability at equal to
a which is not equal to a star will be epsilon
by n okay, and likewise here you have this
probabilities here okay.
So these are the two rather popular ways of
selecting actions in fact epsilon greedy and
soft max are also used in the full reinforcement
learning problem right, it is also used in
the full reinforcement learning problem for
selecting for implementing the exploration
policy right. Now you can convince yourself
that epsilon greedy simply you can convince
yourselves that epsilon greedy right will
give you asymptotic correctness provided something
but can you convince yourself that it will
give you asymptotic correctness right.
You are always going to be taking all the
actions right so eventually you will converge
to the true true expectations right you will
eventually converge to q star because you
are taking all the actions all the time right.
So but what is the problem if I keep my epsilon
fixed at some value let us say I keep epsilon
fixed at 0.1 at 90 percent of the times I
am behaving optimally 10 percent of the times
I choose at random right.
So what will happen I will know the right
q star after a long time, but I will still
be behaving randomly 10 percent of the times
right what asymptotic correctness says is
eventually I should be only giving you the
behaving according to the right arm right.
So I should be only doing the right choice
eventually to achieve that what should you
do, you have to cool epsilon right, so epsilon
has to keep decreasing.
But then you should not decrease it too fast
if you decrease it too fast then you do not
have the guarantee that you will get the correct
q stars right. So there are ways in which
you can balance this right and so in fact
people show that if epsilon falls as 1 by
t right that is usually a sufficient rate,
but unfortunately that will actually slow
down your convergence tremendously because
it becomes truly an asymptotic convergence
I mean you have to run it till infinity for
you to get convergence.
So in practice what you can do is you can
cool it in steps right, set a high epsilon
right, run it for a while okay, and then drop
it a little bit, and then run it for a while,
and then drop it a little bit, then run it
for a while, and so on so forth right. So
the figuring out how long the while should
be is a tricky question depends on a variety
of factors but you can do some kind of empirical
estimates for the time being right good.
So do we move on from here, okay so before
I go on to regret optimality one small thing
which I want to talk about right. So here
I gave you a way of estimating the Qts right.
So what do you notice about that
I run experiments till time t right, and then
when I want to know what Qt is I look back
and see how many times I have taken action
a and then I take the average right. So that
essentially means that at time step t I need
to know what are all the actions I picked
earlier and what were all the rewards I got
for those actions right.
So I need to remember this whole history right.
So is there a more efficient way of doing
it I am sorry, yeah so I can essentially do
this in a kind of doing the run I can do this
running sum right. So how do I do that right,
so I want Qt of a right, so it is some numbers
right. So it is essentially Qt minus 1 of
a right. So let me introduce a little bit
of a notation to make my little easier okay.
So the number of times I have taken action
a I will denote by Na okay, right look at
this okay great.
So assuming that I actually took action a
at this time right, so what will happen okay,
you want me to erase and rewrite both the
numerator and the denominator or only the
denominator, numerator is fine okay I am assuming
this is fine. So now I can do this in a incremental
fashion right, so this is Na by Na plus 1,
Rt by Na plus 1 I can just keep adding this
right.
So I do not need to remember all the rewards
all I need to know is how how many times I
have taken action a so far and what is the
previous estimate of Qt right. If at was not
equal to a what happens this will vanish this
will vanish the Na and Na will get canceled
just the same thing okay so no change. Is
there a different way we can write this, Qt
of a okay, is it fine right, people agree
to that, This is Na by Na plus 1.
So I can write it as 1 minus 1 by Na plus
1 right. Now I can rearrange these quantities
and get a better looking expression, right
looks good. So this is the form of a general
class of equations known as stochastic averaging
equations and there is really no stochasticity
that you need to worry about here but this
is called stochastic averaging equations.
So one way to think about this is I have an
old estimate right and to the old estimate
I add a error term, so what is the error term
this is my target right I should have predicted
the reward is Rt right so this is my target
and that is my actual output right, Q t minus
1 is what I said will be the payoff Rt was
what the what the actual payoff that occurred
right. So Rt minus Q t minus 1 a is some kind
of a error term right.
Now this is some kind of a step size 1 by
Na plus 1 is some kind of a step size. So
what I am doing is I am taking my old estimate
and adding some alpha times an error right.
So many, many iterative algorithms that we
have looked at even if you have taken ML then
some of the algorithms we looked at in ML
right and many iterative algorithms that we
will look at later in the course will all
have this form, old estimate times I mean
plus some alpha times an error term right.
So what is the thing that you should note
here why is it called stochastic averaging
rule, what I am really trying to find out,
what my real target is the what is my real
target, the expected value of Rt the real
target is not Rt right. The real target is
the expected value of Rt right, so my actual
error should have been expected value of Rt
minus Q t minus 1 right, that would have been
my actual error.
But since I do not know the expected value
of Rt so what I am I using here is a some
kind of a measurement of the expected value
right and the unbiased measurement is a sample
drawn from the distribution according to which
you are taking the expectation, when I say
expected value of Rt right Rt is a sample
right, and this is I am going to take the
average of all these samples that is going
to give me the expected value.
Since I do not know the true expectations
I can operate with these samples right. So
I am going to form the estimate of the target
or estimate of the error right by using a
sample as supposed to using the true expectation
that is why we call these as stochastic averaging
rules. And so this is a very standard form
that we will keep seeing again and again in
all the algorithms that we look at right.
So current estimate plus target minus current
estimate right, so this is the thing. And
this particular choice for my alpha here 1
by Na plus 1 gives me the, the exact average
I mean this is exactly I did no approximations
anywhere this gives me exactly the same estimate
as I would have obtained by storing all the
values and taking the average at every time
okay, great.
So we will stop here today or may be I can
just do one more thing and then we can move
on to the other things in the next class.
So far we have assumed that your coins are
not changed right, so we are assuming that
the distributions from which the rewards are
sampled or the payoffs or sample is stationary
okay constant has a different meaning stationary,
stationary means it does not change with time
okay.
So if it is, so when I say something does
not change with time what does it mean, it
means the coin does not change with time,
it does not mean it always comes up heads
okay, when you say something is stationary
okay it does not mean that its outcome is
always the same okay. It means that the distribution
from which I am sampling the outcomes is always
the same okay, but sometimes you might have
non stationary problems right.
So this is essentially keep tossing the coin
the coin one side starts wearing off a little
bit right, so after a while it might start
falling tails more often than heads or what
will happen if the head wears off, will it
start falling heads more often or tails more
often. Start falling heads more often right,
because there will be more metal on the head
side, so it will be heavier so it will tend
to come at the bottom more often.
So if head starts wearing off okay it will
tend to come relatively more frequently on
the top than it used to earlier anyway fine.
So things will start changing over time right
and so what do you do in such cases. So you
need a way I mean there are technical ways
of handling it I am just giving you a practical
way of handling, you need a way to be able
to track the changes over time right.
So if I am going to use this kind of an update
so what will be the problem after I have pulled
arm say 1000 times write this number will
become very small it will be 1 by 1000 plus
1 right it will be 1 by 1000 plus 1 right.
So the impact of the new samples I am drawing
will become smaller and smaller and smaller
right. Suppose I pulled an arm 1000 times
okay 1000 and first time I pulled the arm,
right the impact will be very very small.
And if you think about it, I am averaging
like a 1000 numbers any individual number
is going to have a very small impact on the
average right, but this is all fine if I am
sampling from a stationary distribution, because
I already done 1000 samples what is the 1000
and first sample going to tell me right.
But if I am drawing from a changing distribution
so the more recent samples are more important
to me than the older samples things are changing
my coin is wearing out over time then more
recent samples are more important to me than
the older samples right. So what do I do in
such cases is, where alpha is lesser than
1 so you can do a little bit of expanding
out on this and you can convince yourself
that the as time passes by the older rewards
that I get will get exponentially lesser weight
right.
The first time I do this right the new reward
will get in a weight of alpha right, but second
time I get another reward what will happen
I will get a weight of alpha squared going
in there for the older reward, right the new
reward will still get an alpha the older reward
will get an alpha squared right. So like that
so I will be paying more and more attention
to the newer rewards right, and the older
rewards will keep getting decayed right.
And all I did was very simple change instead
of having 1 by n I made it a constant alpha,
so making it a constant alpha actually allows
me to pay more attention to recent rewards
and less attention to the older rewards right.
And depending on how quickly your rewards
are changing you can tune the value of alpha
right. So problem with keeping alpha fixed
is what, if it is stationary right you will
not converge if it is stationary you still
not converge because you are still paying
attention to the more recent rewards right.
And we will keep oscillating around the true
reward right, so whenever you get a 1 you
will go up, whenever you get a 0 will come
down up down, up down we keep going like that
right because you are paying more attention
to the recent rewards. But the advantage of
keeping alpha constant is that if it happens
to be non stationary right, you track it to
some extent there are other more more robust
ways of tracking non-stationary problems but
this is very simple trick that you can use
right.
And more often than not we will actually end
up using a constant alpha in many of the algorithms
that we will look at and but whenever we talk
about theoretical convergence will always
talk about alpha decay right whenever it look
at practical implementations of this algorithms
will always have a constant alpha right. So
the problem with decaying alpha is 1 by n
is again the same thing which I told you with
decaying epsilon right the changes will become
small very fast right. So that is always a
trade-off that you have to right.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved